<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The eagles flight or six principall notes, or sure markes for euery true Christian to soare vp to the euerlasting nest of Gods eternall kingdome. As it was deliuered in a most godly and fruitfull sermon at Paules Crosse. By Maister Price of S. Iohns in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Price, Henry, 1566 or 7-1600.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10062</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20307</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100876</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836703</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836703</idno>
            <idno type="VID">989</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10062)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 989)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1183:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The eagles flight or six principall notes, or sure markes for euery true Christian to soare vp to the euerlasting nest of Gods eternall kingdome. As it was deliuered in a most godly and fruitfull sermon at Paules Crosse. By Maister Price of S. Iohns in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Price, Henry, 1566 or 7-1600.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[84] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Richard Bradocke for Iohn Busbie, and are to be soulde at his shoppe in Paules church-yard, at the signe of the Crane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E F² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:989:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:989:1"/>
            <p>THE EAGLES FLIGHT Or Six principall notes, or ſure <hi>markes for euery true Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> to ſo are vp to the euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>neſt of Gods Eternall</hi> kingdome.</p>
            <p>AS IT WAS DELIVERED in a moſt godly and fruitfull Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon at Paules Croſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Maiſter Price of S. Iohns in Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by RICHARD BRADOCKE for <hi>Iohn Buſbie,</hi> and are to be ſoulde at his ſhoppe in Paules Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, at the ſigne of the Crane. 1599.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:989:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:989:2"/>
            <head>THE EAGLES FLIGHT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luk. 17 37.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Whereſoeuer the deade bodie is, thither ſhall the Eagles bee gathered together.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ere that fruit a grape (as ſome ſcholemen holde;) or a fig as (with <hi>Moſes Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepha</hi>) <hi>Theodoret</hi> reſolues; or an apple as ſome other ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) for a taſte of which our firſt Parents (Eſau-like) ſould their birthright in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice; Sure I am that (in that) there was not Iuice enough to quench that thirſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter higher knowledge, which the heate of Ambition had bred in the roote of mankinde: But that draught which in his infancie (but like a corne of ſalt) a little diſtempered <hi>Adam</hi> his taſt, ſince (ryſing to a greater growth) like an habituall ſalt
<pb facs="tcp:989:3"/>phlegme, hath bred the paſſion of drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in his poſteritie, that now the more they do know, the more they may know, and the admit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing them to one ſecret is but the hartning them to challendge to be made partakers of another: So itcheth both the eye after the varietie of ſightes, and the care of ſoundes, that (as the wiſe man ſaith) neither is the one ſatiſfied with ſeeing,<note place="margin">Eccl. 1.8.</note> nor the other with hearing. Chriſt no ſoner tooke occaſion by a bold queſtion (which a <hi>Phariſe</hi> aſked him of the time of the day of iudgement) to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe vnto his diſciples the ſignes which might giue them warning of the approch of it, and the ſuddaine ſeperation of the elect from the reprobate; but one preſſed him, and (as it were ſetting ſhoulder to the Portall of Gods very priuie Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,) in they muſt, and bee tolde they muſt where alſo this greate Seſſions ſhould be held.</p>
            <p>Our Sauiour (to leaue a teſtimonie in the worlde how well curioſitie plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him) ſhaps them a kinde of anſwere, which might ſo farre reſolue them as their ſaluation needed, though not ſo
<pb facs="tcp:989:3"/>fully as their humors deſired: and (in a prouerbiall kinde of ſpeach taken from the flight of Fowles vnto their prey) giues them to vnderſtande, that the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct place of this appearance was not to bee enquired after: But a place there ſhoulde bee, in which it ſhoulde bee made, and towardes it ſhould all fleſh as aſſuredly flocke (to receiue their doome) as euer Flowe did to gorge themſelues with their prey.</p>
            <p>Here therefore is a flight of Fowle to a marke: the Fowle that muſt flie are Eagles: the marke (at which the flight muſt bee) is a bodie: the manner (in which this Fowle ſhall flie) is, they ſhall bee gathered togither. And the place (where the marke or bodie ſhall be ſet) is yet vnknowne to theſe Fowles; but whereſoeuer it is, thither ſhall they make repaire.</p>
            <p>By the bodie is ment Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; who at the fulneſſe of time ſhall appeare glorious in that bodie, in which hee once conuerſed with vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned.</p>
            <p>By the Eagles, are vnderſtoode the elect
<pb facs="tcp:989:4"/>&amp; faithfull ſeruants of God, who at this appearance ſhall (as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 36.8.) bee not onely banketed, but euen to the fulnes ſatiſfied, or (as the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal worde ſignifieth) in a ſort ſurcharged with the fatnes of his howſe.</p>
            <p>By the gathering togither of theſe Eagles, is ſhadowed the reſurrection of the iuſt, in which the Trumpe ſhall blow, and the deade ſhall riſe (incorruptible,) and they who haue falne aſleep in Chriſt, ſhall from all the quarters of the worlde bee ſummoued to meete him in the Clowdes.</p>
            <p>By this little therefore that hath beene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oken, ſome ſmall glimſe being giuen of me naturall meaning or drift of this ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: let vs I pray you for the better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of it, enter into a more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler viewe of the ſeuerall parts of it, taking them in order as they lie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereſoeuer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>whereſoeuer</hi> of our Sauiour, is a reply vpon a <hi>Where</hi> (of his diſciples,) whereby in the wordes (next before my Text) they had made bolde to demaund of him of the place in which that ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:989:4"/>ſhould bee of two in one bed, and two in one fielde, and two at one mill, whereof hee had tolde them, that the one ſhould bee receiued, the other refuſed. The originall greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (where Lord) though it more ordinarily import but the places and bee engliſhed <hi>where:</hi> yet alſo ſometime ſignifying the motion to a place, and being fitly tranſlated <hi>whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> (as it appeareth by that one verſe of <hi>Sophocles,</hi> into which in both theſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces hee hath contriued it</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </q>
            <p>makes it probable that they made two demaundes in one worde, one after the place in which this ſentence of ſeparation ſhould paſſe, another after the place into which they (that were thus ſeperated) ſhoule paſſe.</p>
            <p>In effect, firſt to what barre ſhould all fleſh repaire for their doome, then whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſhould bee directed by that doome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Duo quaerentibus vnum respondet</hi> ſaith one; Chriſt ſhapes them but one anſwere to two queſtions. True, but ſuch an one for an anſwere, as the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiues</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:989:5"/>ſay it is, (one for a Sunbeame, which is made of two beames gathered into one) or ſuch a one as you vſe to ſay, two friendes make, which are one in deede in hearte, but two in ſtrength.</p>
            <p>For it cannot bee but the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> of Ten in Two, (the digeſter of ſo large a volume, as the whole lawe into ſo briefe a ſumme, as Loue God aboue all things, and thy neighbour as thy ſelfe) ſhoulde bee as plentifull in his anſwere, as fleſh and bloode ſhould bee in a queſtion, Is their queſtion <hi>where</hi> they ſhould make their appearance? ſee his anſwere, <hi>whereſoeuer</hi> hee ſhall keepe his Court. Is there queſtion whither they ſhall bee tranſlated? See his anſwere, <hi>whither</hi> hee hath gone before to prepare them a place. In fine ſee in one <hi>whereſoeuer,</hi> both a ſnib for the curious, &amp; a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort for the fainting. Firſt a word of the Snib the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a word of the comfort.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereſoeuer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The diuine nature, as it is very mercy it ſelfe, ſo it is alſo very wiſdome it ſelfe: and as in mercy it hath vouchſafed to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part vntoman, that hee ſhall one day bee brought vnto iudgement, ſo it hath in
<pb facs="tcp:989:5"/>wiſdome thought good to conceale from him when ſhall be this day, &amp; where this iudgement into which he ſhall be brought.</p>
            <p>For as the aſſurance of a iudgement (to bee indured) cannot chuſe but worke a feare of often or grieuous offending in a reaſonable man. So it is not vnliklie but that ſo greate fauour as to bee made pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie to the time &amp; place of this iudgement would breed a ſecuritie in the heauie hart &amp; a pride in the ſwelling heart of wicked men. Hereupon th'eternall wiſdome (by whome the world was made) fore ſeing how much more conuenient, the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance than the knowledge of theſe two circumſtances would proue vnto vs, hath in the one preuented, and in the other (as it were) put by our curioſitie.</p>
            <p>For concerning the time,<note place="margin">Mark. 13.32.</note> he cleane diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corageth vs to enquire, elſwher telling vs, that with it not the Angels, nor the Son himſelfe, much leſſe may we be acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And for the place, here giues he vs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as little heart, makeing his Apoſtles (whoſe priuiledge he ſaide it was to know the miſteries of heauen) no directer than an indefinit anſwere, &amp; vouchſafing their
<pb facs="tcp:989:6"/>
               <hi>wher,</hi> not ſo much as a <hi>Here</hi> or a <hi>There,</hi> but putting it by as a demaund which miſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him with an vnreſoluing <hi>wherſoeuer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of which <hi>whereſoeuer</hi> of his, you are not yet to conceiue, as of an anſwere, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee purpoſed to ſhake them off vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as vnreſolued,<note place="margin">Luk. 2.27.</note> (for more liberal of theſe ſecrets then thus was hee, when in a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality hee gaue them to vnderſtand, that hee woulde come in the Clowdes:) but the miſtery which hee refuſeth to breake vnto them, is the particular place or part of this Ayre, where this greate Aſſiſe ſhall be held: which notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet are there (of the peaching lig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of ambitious <hi>Adam</hi>) <hi>Wiſards,</hi> who (as if they had crept into the heart of the Almightie, and ouerheard his ſecrets) would beare the world in hande, that they haue learned and diſtinctly know, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the valley <hi>Ioſaphat</hi> nere <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> at the foote of the hill (from whence the Lord was taken vp into heauen) ſhall this Iudges throne be ſetled. This Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celler, this mightie God (ſo <hi>Eſay</hi> tearmes our Redemer) is ſilent: and yet dares duſt and aſhes preſume to ſpeake? <hi>Whereſoeuer,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:989:6"/>quoth hee (and deſignes no place:) euen here ſay they, and appoint at the valley <hi>Ioſaphat.</hi> True indeede is it, that the Lord will ſummon all nations into the valley <hi>Ioſaphat,</hi> for ſo hath hee promiſed, <hi>Ioel.</hi> 3.2. but whether into material <hi>Ioſaphat,</hi> or <hi>Ioſaphat</hi> ſo tearmed becauſe the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which here ſhall bee pronounced, ſhall reſemble that which there was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted vpon the <hi>Moabites</hi> and <hi>Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uſtly (with <hi>Rapertus Fuitienſis</hi>) doubt. For what is <hi>Ioſaphat</hi> (if you inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret it) but the iudgement of the Lord: and what is the valley, but the depth of that Iudgement, into which <hi>Salomon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures ſures the young man that God will bring him after all the iollitie of his youth, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hee hath cheered himſelfe in the daies of his youth and walked in the way of his heart, and in the ſight of his eyes? <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11.9. Now long theſe men for a reaſon of mee why the Prophet ſhould ſpecifie this place?<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> Ment hee not to teach the Church that heere literally was this Iudge to be expected?</p>
            <p>My anſwere is readie: two reaſons had hee to make choyce of it,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> by alluſion to
<pb facs="tcp:989:7"/>which hee might ſhadowe to the Iewes the day of iudgement: One, the freſhnes of that famous deliuerances memory, which the Lord had wrought in it for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Another, the great reſemblance that will be betweene that generall and that particuler iudgement of his.</p>
            <p>For, from the time of this Prophet yet had there not a mans age paſſed, ſince (without ſtroke of theirs) the Lord had in this valley, within the ſight of this City, diſpatched three whole Armies, which had ioyned forces to beleaguer them; and further in ſuch ſort as in that generall iudgement hee will diſpach the wicked.</p>
            <p>For as here though the <hi>Moabite,</hi> the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monite,</hi> &amp; the inhabitant of <hi>Seyre</hi> bounde themſelues againſt Iuda, Yet cannot they preuaile: So there though the <hi>Moa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiſh</hi> fleſh, the <hi>Amonitiſh</hi> world, the ſauage inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of <hi>Seir</hi> the Diuel, enter a league againſt th'elect, yet ſhall they haue no hand at them. As theirs had, ſo ſhall theſe &amp; their complices haue, ſwords of their owne conſciences accuſing them to turne into their owne bowels.</p>
            <p>And as the ſame place was to them a
<pb facs="tcp:989:7"/>
               <hi>valley of iudgement,</hi> which to the Iewes was <hi>a valley of bleſſing.</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.26. ſo ſhal the great day be to the wicked a day of iudgement, for they ſhall receiue that heauie doome, <hi>go you curſed;</hi> which to the godly ſhall be a day of bleſſing, for they ſhall heare that ioyfull voice <hi>come you bleſſed. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here therfor let proud fleſh take warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to giue ouer inquiry after this ſecret of God: &amp; let careles fleſh take aduice to looke into the ſecret of his own heart. Let it not buſy thee to know where thou ſhalt be iudged, but how thou maieſt anſwere at iudgedment. Knoweſt thou the place? yet canſt thou not withdraw thy ſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, appeare thou muſt. And knoweſt thou not thy ſelfe, ill canſt thou anſwere for thy ſelfe, defenceles wilt thou be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned.</p>
            <p>Bethinke thy ſelfe whether, if here in earth thou wert to come to thine anſwere for a crime pretended to be committed by thee, it were wiſdome to ſpend thy time in harkning after the place of execution, and not rather to imploy it in prouiding thy ſelfe of friends &amp; anſwers againſt the day of thy triall: And then ſay how much
<pb facs="tcp:989:8"/>better thou ſhalt be then madde, if (know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that thou muſt once render an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere of thy life paſt) thou yet wearie thy witte onely in ſearch after the place where, neuer bethinking thy ſelfe ſo much as how thou maieſt render thy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.<note place="margin">Luk. 10.42.</note> Thinkeſt thou not thou ſhalt at laſt haue <hi>Marthaes</hi> checke for troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thy ſelfe about many thinges, where as thou mighteſt with more caſe, haue purchaſed many commendations, &amp; by offending but that one thing which is neceſſarie, haue one of the three (which witneſſe in heauen) giue thee teſtimonie of ſo much diſcretion as to choſe the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part which ſhall not bee taken from thee.<note place="margin">Iohn. 21.22.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This queſtion thou ſeeſt likes thy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour as ill, as that of <hi>Peters</hi> did, what ſhould become of <hi>Iohn:</hi> and therefore propoſe it when thou liſt vnto him, his reply to thee is like to bee as then was to him, buſie bodie what is that to thee? fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thou mee.</p>
            <p>This of the <hi>Snib</hi> (the firſt of thoſe two notes in this <hi>Whereſoeuer</hi>): now a worde of the other, that is the comfort.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:989:8"/>Fleſh and bloode is (naturally) wont in a calme to heed to hope: So in a ſtorme to abiect to deſpaire, and like a Bladder that ſwels indeede with a puffe, but ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recouerably ſhrinks with a pricke.</p>
            <p>Bee wee confronted with no temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and aſſaile there neither perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, our conſtancy, nor croſſe our patience, nor guiltineſſe our peace of conſcience: On ſcowre wee, and ſo high a top beare wee, as to deuoure no leſſe than heauen in expectation. But hap there either the ſmalleſt trouble to fall fowle of vs, or our ſelues a farre off to deſcry the Iuſtice of God with the hiddeouſnes of our owne ſinne: Straight vaile wee Bonnet and (ſcarce haling on) looke for naught, but when wee ſhould wracke. Then can we not heare of a Sauiour, the voice of an accuſer rings ſo lowde in our cares: then can wee not ſee to heauen, the ſteeme of hell hath ſo blinded our eyes, then ſeeme wee ſtill to ſtrike eyther vpon the ſandes of ſome ſecret, or the rocke of our known ſinnes. Riſe wee to the top of a billow? why there is the throne of a iudge to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs. Fall we againe to the bottome?
<pb facs="tcp:989:9"/>why there is a place of torment to follow vs. Then haue wee not memory, for all (euen ſo ſhort a ſpeach as that of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,<note place="margin">Luk. 8.24.</note> 
               <hi>Lord helpe vs or wee periſh:</hi>) But ſo poſſeſt are we with the thought of our owne ende, that no more but the ende of it runnes vpon our tongues, and wee cry onely, <hi>wee periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here, euen ſo conſtant a minde as <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nards (incredibili met<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ac miſerabiliconfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione deiecta,</hi> as hee himſelfe ſpeakes) ſtric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as it were to the grounde with ſo great feare as no heart would thinke but any would pittie: Nay <hi>tenebroſo circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſa horrore,</hi> as it were cloſe priſoner in darkneſſe and horror, <hi>Hoc ſolum,</hi> and that <hi>de profundis</hi> too, <hi>clamabat</hi> as it were from the bottomleſſe pit; will not haue a worde to ſpeake, but <hi>quis nouit pot eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem iraeti lae,</hi> Lord who is able to conceiue aright what the power of thy anger is? And whom doth any feare ſo little ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall, that his wits ſerue him to reckon the torments that attend on thy diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? Here needes not (trow wee) to ſo perplexed a Pilot, as that poore ſoule of ours which God hath ſet at the ſterne of
<pb facs="tcp:989:9"/>this vnwealdie bodie, ſome land-marke to giue it comfort againſt the feare in which it is, and direction for the courſe it is to take? Is it not high time that a Sauiour by a generall <hi>whereſoeuer</hi> ſhould ſhow that Hauen, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deſtroyer by a generall <hi>No-where,</hi> hath almoſt perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded there is no Heauen? yes, and that failes hee not to doe: Heare him (diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſoule) whoſoeuer thou art. Hange ſinne ſo heauie vpon thee, that it ſeemes thou canſt not make any wing, And be the place (to which thou muſt take thy flight) wherſoeuer it will, yet ſhalt thou bee able to recouer it. Faire it with thee as that did with the Doue, and finde thou no other place, yet ſhalt thou not miſſe of thee hande of this <hi>Noah</hi> for thy foote to reſt vpon: <hi>Spectat militem ſuum vbique pugnantem</hi> (as <hi>Ciprian</hi> ſaith) Be it whereſoeuer it will that the aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſet vpon thee, it cannot be ſo darke a place but thy Sauiours eye is vpon thee too, either (if thou faint) to cheere thee, or (if thou fight it out) to Crowne thee.</p>
            <p>Is it the guarde with which this way is kept, that ſcares thee? why is it ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb facs="tcp:989:10"/>than was that of Paradice? It cannot cut thee off.</p>
            <p>Take not an Angell, but Angels, euen Principalities vnto thee, and ioyne they vnto themſelues noe leſſe than Powers. Attende there vpon theſe: death, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch thee: life, to corrupt thee: things preſent, to delight thee: thinges to come, to ſuſpende thee: height, to diſcorage thee: depth, to afright thee: Nay an armie royall of all creatures to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerrunne thee: what greate thinge ſhall they all be able to do? Not ſo much as to ſeperate or with-holde thee, not from the perſon, but neither the very loue, and that is in the hearte thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt; and of whom? of God himſelfe. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38. Know thou no more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culers of this kingdome than <hi>Abraham</hi> did of that which was the type of it: And haue hee which cals thee hither from out thy kinred and from thy fathers houſe, tolde thee no more but that hee will ſhewe thee this Lande: yet paſſe thou on ſecurely: there will come a time, in which, brought to thy iorneyes ende ere thou be a warre, thou ſhalt heare, This
<pb facs="tcp:989:10"/>is the lande which I will giue to thy ſeede: And know thou no more of the coaſte of this way, than <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeruant did of that which ledde to <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuell,</hi> yet relie with him but vpon the conduct of the GOD of his maiſter: and hee ſhall bring thee as ſtraight hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as hee did him whitherſoeuer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The bodie is,</hi> or as <hi>Theophilact</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, and that both in the iudgement of <hi>Hierome,</hi> and vpon the warrant of good reaſon, and euen by the confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Sire-newe Scholiaſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe more ſignificantly, <hi>The deade bodie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this kinde of reading makes both the Syriacke edition of this place, in which for this bodie we reader <hi>Dephegad,</hi> of <hi>Phagad, to deſtroy,</hi> as one woulde ſay the <hi>deſtroyed</hi> or <hi>ſlaine,</hi> And the originall to the fellow text to this in the 24. of <hi>Mat.</hi> where we finde not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to ſal likewiſe, for acakraſſe,<note place="margin">Mat, 24.27.</note> becauſe as <hi>Ierom</hi> ſaith, It falleth by death.
<pb facs="tcp:989:11"/>And the grounde whence this prouerbe in the 39. <hi>Iob.</hi> 33. <hi>verſe,</hi> where euen the vulgar Latine inforced by the nature of the hebrew <hi>Calalim,</hi> comming of <hi>Calal to wound or kill,</hi> reads this, <hi>vbicunque fuerit cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauer flatim adeſt,</hi> Wherſoeuer the carkas or deade bodie is, thither will it (ſpeaking of the Eagle) ſhortly reſort.</p>
            <p>Heere therefore, not to ſay how incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient it may in reaſon bee, to take this body (which ſo many waies is a deade one) for the Church, whoſe verie ſtones Saint <hi>Peter</hi> tels are liuing. 1. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1.51 In this marke, at which this flight is to bee made, there are two things to bee conſidered.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, it is tearmed a bodie: Then this bodie is ſaide to be a deade one: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Both not without ſinguler wiſdome of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>Firſt of the bodie it ſelfe, then of the qualitie of it, it is a deade one.</p>
            <p>Very much is there worth both our attention &amp; memory, in this little which here the Euangeliſt giues our Sauiour, when hee tearmes him a bodie. For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out labour (ſuch is the dexteritie of the
<pb facs="tcp:989:11"/>Spirit of God) both armes hee vs againſt an error, which the Diuell hath ſowne in the Church, and warnes of a benefit, which our God hath beſtowed vpon his Church. For what Chriſtian (hauing his Sauiour tearmed a bodie) is either ſo dull as not to conceiue, that then <hi>Marci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> miſtooke his marke, who taught that hee was but a ſhadowe; or ſo vnthanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as not to recount that for his ſake was this bodie in vnſpeakable humilitie, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed of God in the birth of Chriſt, and in vnconceiueable loue offered vpon the Altar of the Croſſe in the death of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>At this wiſedome ſtand amazed with mee; At this loue, melt with iee, fleſh, if thou be not harder than ſtone. Thy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour is a bodie; reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber this, &amp; with this alſo in the 24. <hi>Luk.</hi> 39. wherewith him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſatiſfied his Diſciples, that he was not a Spirite, For hee had fleſh and bones: and with theſe two texts ſtop the Heretikes mouth, if euer he aſſault thee.</p>
            <p>Thy Sauiour is a bodie, remember this: and with this alſo, that which his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle S. <hi>Peter</hi> tels thee,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.24.</note> that with this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die he hath borne thy ſins vpon the Croſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:989:12"/>and then lift vp thy head and reioyce: let thy thoughts be comforts to thy ſelfe, thy words praiſes to thy God, thy deedes good deeds to thy brethren.</p>
            <p>Thy Sauiour is a body, remember this, &amp; withall that which the Doctour of the Gentils, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.15. tels thee, that thou art a member of this bodie: And then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke thy ſelfe what honor is due to thy bodie: How ill it will beſeeme thee to pollute it with any ſinne, which hee who was without ſin, hath vouchſafed to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept as his own fleſh. Thy Sauiour is a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber this, and with all, That in this body he ſhal returne to iudge the earth. For it was the ſon of man, whom the high Prieſt was promiſed one day to ſee in the Clouds. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.64. And no other but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry him whom they preached, vndertakes <hi>Iohn</hi> vnto the ſoldiers they ſhould behold <hi>Iohn.</hi> 19.37. And to the ſonne hath the father giuen the power to iudge, and by this title as to the ſonne of man <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5 27. And then ſay, whether that ſpeach of <hi>Paule</hi> vnto <hi>Agrippa, Act.</hi> 26.2. will not be fitter for thy mouth than it was euen for his; I thinke my ſelfe happie ſweete Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour
<pb facs="tcp:989:12"/>if I ſhall anſwere this day before thee, Chiefly becauſe thou haſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of all cuſtomes, whether they bee the aduerſaries (who is buſie in aſſalting) or this fleſhes, who is falſe in betraying, or this poore ſoule which is weake in reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. That fleſh of mine, which Iudas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like with a kiſſe to thy Deity deliuered thee into the hands of ſo many Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, hath giuen thee experience of them all. I ſee the woundes yet bleede, which were taken for my ſins, and loe my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is aſſiſtant in iudgement to aſſure mee it ſhall be pattaker in glorie.<note place="margin">Gen. 43, 34,</note> Is my <hi>Ioſeph</hi> thus greate? then ſhall not his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Beniamins</hi> entertainement bee ſmall. And if <hi>Heſter</hi> be ſo deare to <hi>Aſſuerus,</hi> ſure her kinſman <hi>Mardochy</hi> ſhall haue his day.<note place="margin">Heſt, 6, 1.</note> There is in ſtore for him a robe and a ring and a horſe, and a crowne, and a traine to proclame his ſauour, Thus ſhal it be done to the man whom the king will honour. Thy Sauiour is a bodie, remember this, &amp; withall that which himſelfe hath auerred in the ſixt of <hi>Iohn,</hi> That this bodie and fleſh of his is meate indeede, and then neuer doubt but thou ſhalt haue where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall
<pb facs="tcp:989:13"/>to ſtrengthen thine heart.</p>
            <p>Let the windowes of heauen be ſhut, that the raine cannot fall to moiſten; let the face of the ſkye bee darkned that the Sunne cannot breake out to ripen; let the poores of the earth be locked that the fruite cannot ſpring forth to feede thee: yet art thou prouided for thy diet.</p>
            <p>Thy Sauiour his bodie ſhall bee to thee the widdowes Barrell and Cruſe: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhall this meale (if I may ſo terme it) of his fleſh,<note place="margin">1, King, 17 16,</note> nor this Oyle of his blood faile thee. The meate that hee will giue thee endureth vnto euerlaſting life.</p>
            <p>So ſaith himſelfe, <hi>Iohn,</hi> 6.27. The wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that hee will giue ſhall be to him that drinketh of it, a Well of water ſpringing to euerlaſting life: ſo vndertakes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4.14. Findes the Fowle her prey delightfull when ſhe tyres vpon it? Bee ruled by <hi>Dauid, Come and taſt of thy Lord and thou ſhalt finde him more than ſo, no leſſe than euen ſweete.</hi> Finds the Fowle her prey hartie,<note place="margin">Heb, 10, 22,</note> and growes ſhee high by tyring vpon it? Bee aduiſed by Saint <hi>Paule, Drawe neare thy Sauiour, with a
<pb facs="tcp:989:13"/>pure heart in aſſurance of faith, and thou ſhalt finde him more than ſo.</hi> Such fulnes ſhalt thou meete with (in him,) wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of not thou, but wee all, both may &amp; doe receiue: and what receiue wee? no meaner things than very grace, and it not mincingly, But ſo thinke,<note place="margin">Iohn. 1.16.</note> as grace for grace, or, as ſome interpret, grace vpon grace, or grace in the necke of grace, <hi>Pro Legis gratia, Gratiam Euangelij</hi> (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeakes.) In time paſt the grace of the lawe, but it not ſeruing to bring vs to God: In the fulneſſe of time the grace of the Goſpell, and with this one grace (as with one hande manie fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers) how many graces? The grace of <hi>Redemption,</hi> for to purchaſe it vnto vs, he giues himſelfe who is this bodie, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6. The grace of ſpirituall growth; for both is his age <hi>The meaſure,</hi> and his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, <hi>The meanes</hi> of this growth of ours. The grace of <hi>Sanctification:</hi> for this that hee might conferre on vs,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.13.</note> fanctified hee himſelfe. The grace of <hi>Glorification:</hi> for (to harbing as it were,<note place="margin">Iohn. 17.19.</note> &amp; to prepare for our inſtalment therein) is hee before aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended into heauen, ſo that ſparing is his
<pb facs="tcp:989:14"/>commendations of our ſauiour, as the Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">Iohn, 14, 2 Pſal, 45, 2</note> full of grace are not his lips on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but his whole bodie alſo.</p>
            <p>In whatreſpect Chriſt is termed a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, you ſee: why a deade one, let vs now inquire.</p>
            <p>May it bee in regarde of the eſtate wherin he either now is, or hereafter may bee? No, hee hath had his <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>perſedeas</hi> for death, euer ſince his reſurrection. Chriſt once ryſing from death,<note place="margin">Rom, 9, 6</note> dieth no more, death hath no more dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him. And though himſelfe confeſſe that he was deade, yet addes he, that now the caſe is altered: For why? he is aliue, &amp; that not for a time but for euermore Amen.<note place="margin">Reue, 1, 18</note>
            </p>
            <p>The tearme therefore of being deade, which here the Euangeliſt giues him, hath relation to a ſtate of his which is paſt. For hee was indeede (as you haue heard) de ade:<note place="margin">Exo, 12 46</note> witneſſe the ſouldiers who becauſe they fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d him ſo, vnwittingly ful filled the ſcripture, whilſt they ſaued the needleſſe paines,<note place="margin">Iohn, 19, 33,</note> as they tooke it, of brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his legges: And had he not ſo beene, hard of digeſtion would our weake-ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mackt
<pb facs="tcp:989:14"/>faith haue found him.</p>
            <p>For as in the lawe,<note place="margin">Leuit, 17, 13,</note> were it beaſt or fowle that was taken by trauell, ſuch as for his kinde might lawfully bee eate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> yet muſt the bloode of it bee ſhed a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> couered with duſt ere it were eaten <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the goſpel were this Lambe which we had not caught indeede,<note place="margin">Gen, 27, 20,</note> but which (as <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaide of his veniſon) the Lord our GOD hath brought it into our hands, neuer ſo cleane (and indeede without ſpot of ſinne was it) yet muſt his ſide be opened with the ſpeare, and his body hid in the duſt of the graue, before he coulde be diet for our ſoules.</p>
            <p>Phiſitions both in their directions in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, preſcribe the fleſh of the doue as wholſome, and in their practiſe applye the bloode of it a ſoueraigne againſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine diſeaſes of no baſer parts than the eye, and the braine. For <hi>Galen</hi> in his tenth booke of the vertue of Symples giues it againſt the bruſes called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which make euery thinge wee looke on ſeeme redde. And <hi>Iul. Alex. liber</hi> 12. <hi>Capite</hi> 4. <hi>ſalubrium</hi> commendeth it as a moſt ſpeciall baulme
<pb facs="tcp:989:15"/>to bee dropped vpon the corners off the Braine called <hi>Pia</hi> and <hi>dura mater,</hi> in the woundes of the heade: which though they doe, yet in the feare of infla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on councell they a kinde of diuorce of theſe two ſo wholeſome parts, and wiſh this birde to bee let bloode eare it bee eaten.</p>
            <p>Not vnlike is the caſe of this harmeleſſe and guiltleſſe doue our Sauiour, vpon whom ſo many of vs (as be right Eagles) muſt prey:<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.50.</note> wholſome is his fleſh, for of it who ſo eateth ſhall not die. So preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous is his bloode, had it not beene dropt vpon theſe eyes of ours, yet had wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in our bloode, and (loked wee whither wee coulde,) ſtill ſhoulde wee haue bene troubled with theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: No where could we haue founde a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanter ſpectacle than the goare of our ſinnes: And had it not beene applyed to that wounde which we tooke in our head <hi>(Adam,)</hi> died had both hee and wee of it.</p>
            <p>Yet ſee, ſtroken muſt he bee, eare we can be healed:<note place="margin">Eſay. 53.5</note> For by his ſtripes are we made whole. Dye muſt hee that wee
<pb facs="tcp:989:15"/>may liue, for his life it is that this good ſhepheard muſt lay downe for his ſheepe. And ſpilt muſt his bloode bee,<note place="margin">Iohn. 10.14. 1 Co. 5.50 1. Iohn. 1.7, Mat. 26.28,</note> that we might bee purged from that bloode, to which poſſeſſion of the kingdome of heauen is denyed. For his bloode is it which clenſeth vs from all our ſinnes, and the way by applying this bloode is by ſhedding it.</p>
            <p>Wee reade in the greeke ſtorie of one <hi>Codrus</hi> king of the <hi>Athenians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iuſtin.</note> who in the time of warre betweene his people and their neighbours of <hi>Peloponneſus,</hi> being by the Oracle, a putatiue Dietie, to which in time of <hi>Paganiſme</hi> they had recourſe for councell, admoniſhed that theirs ſhoulde the day bee whoſe king was by the enemie ſlaine, to purchaſe his Armie victorie entred this courſe; hauing clad himſelfe in baſe attire, hee priuily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaide himſelfe to the enemies Campe, where offering ſuch ſpeaches of defiance as coulde not bee borne at ones hande ſo meane in ſhowe, in rewarde of his bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes hee was ſlaine: vpon which ſucceſſe enſued vnto the <hi>Athenians,</hi> as the Oracle had foretolde, and conquerers they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came.
<pb facs="tcp:989:16"/>Thus kinde, &amp; kinder was our <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drus</hi> our prince of peace, knowing not by any deceitfull information of a doubting Oracle, but by that infallible wiſdome, whereby hee vnderſtandeth all thinges, that eyther hee muſt accept of death, or wee might not hope to aſpire to life, ſuch were the bowels of his loue, that firſt hee denied as it were to drawe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the glorie of his Dietie this vile clothing of our fleſh, and then ſo diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed went at hell mouth to chalenge our enemie, who toald on with the baſenes of his outward appearance, quickneth many, while hee thought to kill one: <hi>Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lente illum malignitate ſua</hi> (as a Father ſaith) <hi>dum intulit ſupplicium filio Dei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leo.</note> 
               <hi>quod cunctis hominum filijs on remedium verte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur:</hi> ouerdrawne euen in his own bowe, and buſie to haſten on the Sonne of Gods execution, with all the ſonnes of mens redemption. <hi>Ruens dumirruens, captus dum capit, dum mortalem perſequitur in ſaluatorem incidens:</hi> falling whilſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, caught whilſt catching, and in the heate of his purſuite after, as hee thought, a mortall man, confronted by
<pb facs="tcp:989:16"/>the puiſſance of the eternall Cod.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> king of the Epirotes hauing in two ſet battels with greate loſſe of men put the Romanes, the Lordes of the worlde, to the worſt, and hearing by a fauorite of his, this his ſo greate good fortune: ſmothingly gratulated him, that two victories indeede he had gotten of them, but them ſo deare, that ſhoulde hee at the ſame rate buy a third, the purchaſe would no leſſe than vndoe him.</p>
            <p>A greater complaint than this may the prince of darkeneſſe take vp, ſo deare hath this one comming forth at Chriſt coſt him, that the mortgaging of his kingdome will not beare the charge of a ſeconde conflict: For what did Chriſt in this conflict? euen Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian-like <hi>Viuit cadendo</hi> through death hee no leſſe than deſtroyed him, who had power of death, neither had hee other meanes left to attaine this ſo glorious a conqueſt.<note place="margin">Heb, 4, 27 2, 14, Exod, 30, 16,</note> In thee muſt into the ſecond Tabernacle; thither was no acceſſe without bloode: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion muſt hee procure; that could
<pb facs="tcp:989:17"/>hee not without ſhedding of bloode:<note place="margin">Heb, 9, 22.</note> A kingdome hee had by will to bequeath, that could not bee entred vpon, till by his death it were inforced:<note place="margin">Heb. 9, 17 Rom, 6, 3</note> For what is our tenure by which wee holde of him? Is it not this death of his? Not into his birth, but into his death are wee baptized.</p>
            <p>True it is which <hi>Fulgentius</hi> hath: <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula vitiatae propaginis inde incepit aboleri, vude in vnoquoque naſcentium videbatur exiſtere:</hi> As wee were ſinnets in the Cradle, ſo was Chriſt our Sauiour in the Manger. And on foote indeed was our ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uation, the firſt inſtant he was in the fleſh; but noe more but in hande was it, till the laſt moment hee was fitte to bee in the graue. Hee beganne our exaltati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on when he reſolued vpon his owne hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation: And after paſt there him not ſo much as an idle action, but ſtill buſie was hee to ſatiſfie for our rebelling by his obeying, for our ſurfeting by his faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for our blaſphemie by his praying, for our wronging by his ſuffering: Yet neuer ſway hee an iſſue of all this, till wee ſawe that iſſue of two ſtreames out of his ſide, The ſouldiers ſpeare was
<pb facs="tcp:989:17"/>the penne, &amp; his bloode the inke, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with hee ſigned: And that triumphant <hi>conſummatum eſt,</hi> it is finiſhed, the Seale hee ſet to his <hi>quietus eſt,</hi> or diſcharge of ours.</p>
            <p>Threatned hee had death by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. <hi>Hoſe.</hi> 6.13. that he would bee his death: yet heare wee not him vndertake as if he had beene as good as his worde, till after his paſſion: hee muſt bee lifted vp and then will hee draw all men vnto him? Then dare his Apoſtle make bolde with death,<note place="margin">Ioh. 12, 32 1, Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.55</note> and aſke it where is his ſting? and with the graue, and demaunde of it where is his victorie? Vpon point of his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, according to his prophecie that the children of the Brydall ſhould mourne when the Bridegrome was taken from them, his diſciples grewe out of heart: to comfort them he tels them of a conqueſt of his, I haue ouercome, ſaith hee: but what? No more but the firſt of the three combats of the worlde; I haue ouercome the worlde.<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1. Cor. 15.26.</note> That laſt enemie (death) was yet to be grapled with; who <hi>(tanquam Briareus)</hi> for his vallour being ſet as it were to guarde the ſtandard of hel, could
<pb facs="tcp:989:18"/>not bee eaten with looking vpon. But ſo harde a ſkirmiſh was to be endured in the quelling of him, as after a retreate againe and againe to his father, with if it bee poſſible let this cup paſſe from mee, ſhould coſt the victor a ſweate, and it not naturall, but euen a ſleete of water mixed with bloode.</p>
            <p>Heere therefore is the vſe of this title here giuen this bodie: deade it is termed to aſſure you yee ſhall liue; And ſtrucken is the blood of you paſcall Lamb Chriſt Ieſus, vpon the dore-poſt (as I may terne it of your houſes, that is in each of your viewes, that it may ſerue to ſecure you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deſtroyer.</p>
            <p>For as in the full of the Moone, where the landlord of light the Sunne, and his freeholder the Moone be farthe ſtaſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, the Sun is no ſooner ſet, but you looke, and are not decieued, the that Moone ſhould ſtraight ariſe: Euen ſo in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of time, in which your ſinnes had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated (as the Prophet ſpeaketh) bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene you and your God, the Lord of your life,<note place="margin">Eſa. 59.2.</note> no ſooner ſet in the Weſt of his deth, but he drew vp al you, that are light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:989:18"/>by him, into the Aſcende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of your new life.</p>
            <p>Now therefore as it is written of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lephants,<note place="margin">1. Mac. 6.34.</note> that they grow fearce by the ſight of the blood of the grape ſpilt before them ſo will it bee expected at all your hands, that this bloode of your Sauiour (which is the true vine) thus powred out before you, put ſtomach in all you againſt the power of darknes: and that you fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low where you General hath led, march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to life, if it were to death, and dying to ſinne ſince bee hath died for ſinne, Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vanitie vnderſtande you haue not an eare to heare it, and leaſing you haue not a tongue to ſpeake it, &amp; malice you haue not a hart to conceine it, &amp; pride you haue not an eye to admit it, and gluttony you haue not a ſtomach to banquet it, and a bride you haue not a hand to receiue it, &amp; ſin you haue not a minde to commit it. You reade in the <hi>Pſalme,</hi> of the death of a Saint whith is pretious in the ſight of the Lord; <hi>Haec eſt illa mors</hi> (ſaith <hi>Leo</hi>) why this is the death GOD hath in ſo high re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, <hi>Vbi h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mo occiditur in mundo, non terminatione ſenſuum ſed fine vitiorum</hi> when a man dies, before hee dies,
<pb facs="tcp:989:19"/>and ſhakes handes, not with his ſences but with his ſinnes.</p>
            <p>This of the deade bodie, or marke at which this flight is: now of the flight it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thither ſhall the Eagles bee gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therin:
<list>
                  <item>Firſt of the ende of their flight.</item>
                  <item>Then of the choyce of the fliers.</item>
                  <item>And laſt of the manner of their flying</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The ende whither they ſhall make: Thither.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The flyers: who they ſhall be: Eagles.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Their flights: In what manner it ſhalbe: <hi>Thither ſhall theſe Eagles bee gathered together.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thither: both aloft into the ayre to meete their Iudge, and aboue into the heauens to raigne with their God.</p>
            <p>Thither: for their doome for there they ſhall receiue that Patent for a kingdome, <hi>Come ye bleſſed, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thither, for the crowne: for where him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is, euen there is that our Sauiours will, there whome his Father hath giuen him bee they:<note place="margin">Iohn. 17.</note> where an Angell ſhall bee the
<pb facs="tcp:989:19"/>Clarke, Meſſias the Iudge, Saints the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Innocent the verdict, <hi>Receiue a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> the ſentence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thither ſhall the Eagles bee gathered togither:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where the glorie of their God, whoſe brightneſſe they ſhall ſe: their ſafety from their foes, whoſe ruine they ſhall behold: the comfort of the Saints, whoſe company they ſhall enioy: the receipt of a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, vpon receipt of which they ſhall enter the Fee ſimple of life, which they ſhall neuer looſe: the temper of their ioy, which ſhall ſatiſfie, and yet not glut, ſhall ioyne and ſtryue to fill them with happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thither ſhall. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where is a citie, and the gates of it Pearle, and the ſtreetes of it Golde, and the Walles of it Pretious ſtones, and the Temple in it, the almightie God, and the light of it, the Lambe; and the Veſſels to it, Kings of the earth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thither ſhall. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where is a riuer, and the ſpring of it, the Throne of God, and the water of it Chriſtall, and the Bankes of it are ſet with
<pb facs="tcp:989:20"/>the trees of life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thither ſhall &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where the cheere is ioy: the exerciſe, ſinging: the city praiſe: the Subiect, God. the Quire, Angels.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thither ſhall, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where there ſhal be no more neede to feare leaſt either the eyes be dimmed with teares, or the ſoule ſurpriſed by death, or the heart damped with ſorrow, or the eares a frighted cries, or the ſences doſturbed with paine. For from thence (whither theſe ſhall bee gathered) ſhall all they depart farre away: Where they ſhall bee good and not perſecuted, happy and not enuied, rich &amp; not robbed, kings and not flattered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thither ſhall, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where they ſhal haue poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s without inpeachments, Seignories without cares, length of years without decay of ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, loue of all without ielouſie of any, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſtate without conſcience of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thither ſhall, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where they ſhal be togither in the ſame inſtant rauiſhed with ſeeing, ſatisfied
<pb facs="tcp:989:20"/>with enioying, and ſecured for retaining.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thither ſhall, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O then how happie they who ſhal bee gathered thither! coulde this heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it, or this tongue tell it, or theſe cares heare it, then were they tranſlated thither. O then how had pie they who ſhal bee gathered? But who they? <hi>Non qualiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque</hi> (ſaith <hi>Origen</hi>) not ot euery fether I wiſſe.</p>
            <p>Wee haue Peacoks, all whoſe glory is their Plumes, they are all readie; but too too ſquare: they ſhal not do well to ſpred: They are not they.</p>
            <p>Wee haue Vultures, all whoſe Tenure is in their pompe, they are all ready, but too too high, they ſhall not do well to towre They are not they.</p>
            <p>Wee haue ſparrowes, all whoſe ſporte is in their luſt, they are all readie, but too too pleaſant, they ſhall not doe well to Chirpe: They are not they.</p>
            <p>We haue Oſtriches, all whoſe feeding is on mettels, they are too too ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloide, they ſhall not doe well to ſtretch:<note place="margin">In Mat. tract. 30,</note> They are not they.</p>
            <p>We haue Cormora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: whoſe God is their
<pb facs="tcp:989:21"/>belly, they are all readie, but too too fed, they ſhall not doe well to gape, They are not they.</p>
            <p>All they to this Thither are Scarabees or Beetles, and it to them a Roſe, It is ſo ſweete it kils them.</p>
            <p>The breath of man if you marke it, hath this propertie at the ſame inſtant to warn that which is neere it, and to coole that which is farre off So fares it with the Lord of Hoſtes.</p>
            <p>Is one neare him?<note place="margin">Pſal. 85.9.</note> (and ſo is euery one that feareth him) then warme lights the breath of this Thither vpon him, and ſo cordiall is it,<note place="margin">Wiſd. 1.3.</note> as is no confection of the Apothe caries. But let one be farre off him, and leſſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not any be who lodgeth wicked thoughts, for they ſeperate from God, then bleake comes it to his heart, &amp; a very ſhaking ſends it through his bones.</p>
            <p>Then ſownds Thither to the graue, as to the goale, to iudgement as the Aſſiſe, to Hell as the place of execution.</p>
            <p>Then, where is a iudge and his preſence worſe to bee endured than the waight of Mountaines, it is ſo fearefull, where are thouſands of home-borne witneſſes, and
<pb facs="tcp:989:21"/>their euidences againſt thee, al are ſo cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el; where a ſentence ſhall paſſe, and it, <hi>Go you curſed,</hi> It is ſo ſeuere:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is their Thither.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where an execution is done, and the officer the Diuell: And the Inſtrument of Fier, and the kind, Burning; and the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure eternitie,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is their Thither.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O then how curſed they who ſhal bee gathered thither?</p>
            <p>But who they? All ſaue ſo many as ſhall be gathered to that other Thither. But who they? Harken and hee will tell you who muſt bring you thither: Eagles, not a wing of other male ſhall bee gathered thither. For it is like lightning that this Iudge toulde you hee will come: And lightning, you know,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.27.</note> no bird but the Eagle will broake. Now ſhoulde you doubt who theſe Eagles bee, and aſke firſt of Origen, hee will anſwere in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, <hi>Qui in paſſionem domins credunt,</hi> They which Iay holde vpon Chriſts paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Then of <hi>Hiero,</hi> and hee will returne, <hi>Sancti,</hi> The ſame, but in fewer wordes: Then of <hi>Cyrill,</hi> and hee will iumpe with
<pb facs="tcp:989:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Ierome</hi> both in ſence and wordes, <hi>Sancti</hi> the Saints: Then of <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and he will tell you in effect as much,<note place="margin">2 Chro. 5.13.</note> 
               <hi>Inſtorum Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae,</hi> the ſoules of the iuſt.</p>
            <p>Thus like Salomons noiſe of Prieſts, which ſounded trompets at his bringing in the Arke into his temple, they were of the citie of <hi>Dauid</hi> as theſe are (that is) of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> which is from aboue, were there no fewer than 120. of them, yet ſuch an Vni-ſound would they all keepe, that you would ſay they were as one blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing Trompets, &amp; that they ſang and made but one ſounde in ſinging.</p>
            <p>But would you in particuler knowe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you be anie of thoſe Eagles yea orno, And by conſequent whither you ſhall be gathered togither? Take of mee 6. notes of an Eagle that will not faile you.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Your Neſt,</item>
               <item>2 Your eye,</item>
               <item>3 Your Flight</item>
               <item>4 Your Foe,</item>
               <item>5 Your Age,</item>
               <item>6 Your witte,</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>1 If it be on the Rocke.</item>
               <item>2 If it can broke the Sun.</item>
               <item>3 If it be high and ſwift.</item>
               <item>4 If it be the Dragon.</item>
               <item>5 If it be well renewed.</item>
               <item>6 It it bee firſt to peaſe, then to carie what you ſeaze on.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:989:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>By each of which, that you may be better able to examine your ſelues, I will by God his aſſiſtance ſpeake a worde of each.</p>
            <p>Be you right bred therefore,<note place="margin">Iohn 309, 1.30.31.</note> Firſt you will not build but vpon the rock: for ſo ſaith <hi>Iohn.</hi> The Eagle makes her neſt on high, ſhe abideth on the rock, euen vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the toppe of the rocke; So farre will you bee either from the negligence of ſome, who pearch they care not where: or the pride of other ſome who builde high enough, but not ſure enough: or the ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of other ſome, who neſt in the ruines of the rocke.</p>
            <p>There is a firſt kinde of men, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing caught <hi>Iuſtus ex fide ſua vinet,</hi> the iuſt ſhall liue by faith by the ende, runne away counter with <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> they haue founde, and flatter themſelues with a conceipt that the waie forſooth to heauen they cannot looſe, follow they the trace of <hi>Arrius,</hi> yea almoſt of <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> himſelfe.</p>
            <p>For the iuſt (that is, ſaie they, the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallie-honeſt man) ſhall liue, that is, ſhall bee admitted into the ioyes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by his faith, that is in the lieu
<pb facs="tcp:989:23"/>of that kinde of deuotion or religion whereto he addicted himſelfe, be it what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it will.</p>
            <p>Be any of you of this fether &amp; ſo head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die as to take that way which commeth next to hande, for the next way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.4.</note> hee is no Eagle, he buildeth not on the Rocke. For the Rocke is Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and beſides him there is not giuen a name by which they may bee ſaued.</p>
            <p>As it fared with <hi>Paules</hi> fellow-paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in their wracke, the ſhippe (continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed they in it) woulde ſaue them all: but the ſhipboate were it kept in to it, would looſe all. So fareth it in this wrack of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, Bee this rocke Chriſt built v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, hee will ſecure all: But bee any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sauiour relyed vpon, hee will no leſſe than faile all.</p>
            <p>As of the priuiledge his death had in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing alone, it is excellently ſaide, <hi>multo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp;c.</hi> Many a Saints death hath beene pretious in the ſight of the Lord, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a one to bee ſo innocent as the ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of the whole worlde: <hi>Solus dominus noſter Ieſus Chriſtus extitit, in quo omnes crucifixi, omnes mortui, omnes ſepulti, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:989:23"/>etiam ſuſcitati.</hi> One Chriſt Ieſus is found, through whoſe ſide all men are crucified, with whoſe laſt gaſpe all men gaue vp the ghoſt, in whoſe graue all men are buried, by whoſe reſurrection all men are quickned: Euen ſo of the priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his faith hath, may it bee as truely added <hi>Multorum inconspectu hominum specioſa fides:</hi> many another religion hath beene a faire ſhewe in the ſight of men, but none of them could iuſtifie before God. Onely a true faith in Chriſt Ieſus hath beene able to crucifie the heate of luſt, to kill the heate of concupiſcence, to bury the memorie of ſinne, &amp; to quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the life of righteouſnes. The life which is gained by knowing him hath a ſingling <hi>Haec</hi> in the foreheade of it; <hi>Haec eſt vita aeterna,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 17.3.</note> this is the eternall life in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, to know thee, and the Ieſus thou haſt ſent. And this is that one faith which is compaſſed in with ſo glorious a couple, as one God before and one Baptiſme behind.</p>
            <p>There is a Second kinde who build,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.5</note> 
               <hi>&amp; ſuper altitudmem</hi> too (indeede aloft) but it is <hi>cordis ſui</hi> (as <hi>Iuſt</hi> ſaith) the loft of
<pb facs="tcp:989:24"/>their owne prowde he art: And this hart of theirs (as in an Anatomy you know it is) like the Poets <hi>Pernaſſus</hi> being <hi>Biceps</hi> double-ridged, hauing a left knoll puffed vp with the conceipt of innocencie in ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtayning from euill, and a right (and yet wrong) ſwollen with opinion of deſert by doing good, hath giuen ſite to two other miſ-builders, neither of which can make good that they are Eagles: for they builde not on the rocke.</p>
            <p>The one ſort, our young Angelicall maiſters, whome <hi>Donatus</hi> hath had the ſcowring of, and left them nothing but puritie.</p>
            <p>The other our old Meritours, who are ſo farre before-hand, as to haue made euen with God for the purchaſe of heauen.</p>
            <p>The former would be reputed ready in the Text: were they ſo, they coulde not (mee thinkes) but meete with that Reba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, (at leaſt would they marke it) in the fourth of <hi>Iames,</hi> we offende: &amp; who? not only a few worldlings, which will heare a ſermon at the Croſſe, but all new re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants too, and that not in one or two, but in many things: In many things wee
<pb facs="tcp:989:24"/>offende all: Or that through-cooler in the 65. of <hi>Eſay.</hi> 5. where they heare better newes of theſe perfect ons, who were ſo much holyer than the reſt:<note place="margin">Eſay. 65.5</note> that none muſt preſſe into their company: then that they were as ſmoake in the wrath of the Lord and a fire that burneth all the day long.</p>
            <p>The latter would be eſteemed as preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in the Fathers: were they ſo, They could not (mee thinks) miſſe: of eyther that of <hi>Leo</hi> (It is ſo obuious) <hi>Neceſſarium eſt trepidare de monito, Religioſum gaude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re de dono:</hi> Be thou neuer ſo good, yet muſt thou learne to builde ſo little on it, as to tremble at the thought of it: And bee heauen giuen neuer ſo free coſt, yet ſo, downe muſt thy ſtout hearte, on this condition to bee glad to accept it: Or that of <hi>Bernardus, Merita habere cures, merita data noueris frùctum, speres dei miſeric ordiam.</hi> Doe not like the men of this barren generation of ours, who (as ſecurely as they ſit) are the next doore to curſing, and in the way to burning too:<note place="margin">Heb. 6.</note> for thats the iſſue they ſhoulde finde of ſo little
<pb facs="tcp:989:25"/>fruite after ſo long tilling. Bee doing a Gods name, and God (though he will not ſell the) yet will giue thee heauen but yet ſee thou bee ſure to remember of whom it is giuen thee to be able to do this good, and then in any caſe let thy Plea be, <hi>Not mine owne merit but his mercie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A third ſort of men there is who build, and about the rocke too, but not on the top of the rocke, as <hi>Iob</hi> tels vs the Eagles doe, but where the ſtorme hath worne a hole in the rocke, Theſe are rather <hi>Plinies</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo termed, becauſe they naturally want feete and cannot ſtand, in engliſh <hi>Martinets,</hi> who as the ſame Author <hi>lib.</hi> 10 <hi>chap.</hi> 39. of his naturall hiſtory writeth, haue certaine good qualities.</p>
            <p>Firſt they bee very rife court and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try ſwarme with them. Then they are as buſie as rife, <hi>His quies niſi in nido nulla, aut pendent aut iacent,</hi> They are ſtill ſtirring, but in their neſts, and there you ſhall not take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but either hanging or lying. Laſt they are as diuerſe as either rife or buſie, <hi>&amp; ingenia aequè varia,</hi> ſcarce two of them in one minde.</p>
            <p>Firſt they builde in the Ruines of the
<pb facs="tcp:989:25"/>Rocke: for what betwene the ſacrilegious preferrer, which will not beg all but haue ſome: And the Simonicall gratifier, who like our new kinde of purchaſers, makes away land to get Lordſhippes by ſea: and the fantaſtique Reformer, <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nomine im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perij impugnat imperium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act, 5.38.</note> who hath beene ſo long building the Church, till hee hath almoſt puld downe the Church (for there are more kinde of <hi>Martinets</hi> than the <hi>Libellers</hi>) neuer wrought <hi>Hannibals</hi> ſcalding vineger vpon the Alpes, as theſe fellowes, as hote as tart Spirits, doe vpon this poore Rocke (the Church) to make it moulder downe. But the comfort is, they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they haue noe feete. For if <hi>Paule</hi> his tutors rule holde, and by Saint <hi>Luke</hi> (regiſtring it) it ſhould ſeme it doth, This councell of theirs, which is not of God, cannot ſtand: the roote of that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee but rottenneſſe, whoſe fruite is but corruption, and no longer can this fog of their greatneſſe laſt, than till the Sunne be riſen to diſpell it; and towards day it cannot but alreadie bee, ſo many Cocks haue crowed againſt them.</p>
            <p>This of the firſt note of an Eagle, the
<pb facs="tcp:989:26"/>neſt, and ſuch as by it may be knowne to be no Eagles.</p>
            <p>Now a worde of the ſecond to witte the eye, which (be you of the right male) is al waies ſo quicke as to ken a farre off, &amp; ſo ſtrong as to looke ſtraight againſt the Sunne. For her eyes behold a farre off ſaith <hi>Iob:</hi> &amp; <hi>Plin. lib.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Illi acies contra radios ſolis ſtat firma,</hi> her eye will neuer water though ſhe gaſe into the Sun. And theſe two vertues ſhall you ſtill marke in their eyes who ſhall bee gathered hither.<note place="margin">Iob. 39.32</note> See the firſt in <hi>Abraham,</hi> in whoſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome <hi>Diues</hi> would faine haue beene: he can ſee and reioyce at Chriſts day almoſt 2000. yeares off. See the ſecond in Eagle <hi>Iohn</hi> himſelfe, and his fellowes he runnes not with bare <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (wee haue ſeene) but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.56.</note> our eyes haue ſerued vs to ſtande and gaſe vpon no leſſe than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen his glorie: yet what manner glory was his? very ſuch as is the onely begotten ſonnes of the Father.</p>
            <p>Gratious God, how farre are the <hi>Atheiſts</hi> of our age from both this ſtrength and ſharpnes of ſight! Light it ſelfe is ſo dym they cannot ſee it: themſelues are ſo farre
<pb facs="tcp:989:26"/>off they cannot diſcerne themſelues, for God is light (ſo ſaith the truth,) and their ſoules are themſelues, ſo faies their Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie.</p>
            <p>They cannot ſee a God (that is the fountain of al natures) in ſo cleare a glaſſe as the Mirrour of all creatures. A worke ſo faire would in reaſon proue a worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man as ſkilfull. For to an effect aboue the bent of his owne nature, can no cauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny better reach, than a childes wit can to the building of this Church. And yet can they (Buſſards as they are) ſee a worlde, that is a building, infinity admirable for the firmnes, capacitie, maieſtie, vſe, order, motion of it: And not finde as much as the tracte of any creatures either omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in that fitmenes, or infinitneſſe in that capacitie, or glorie in that maieſtie, or goodneſſe in that vſe, or wiſdome in that order, or life in that motion of it.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe one of theſe pollitike depoſe-Gods were but a maiſter Chimick (as ſuch working wits are verie ingenious) &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing don me the fauour to ſhew me ſome one of his eſpecial Magiſtrals (as greatnes
<pb facs="tcp:989:27"/>of ſkill, &amp; pride in kindenes are oft co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions) ſhould heare me iudge it to be the deſtillation of ſome Pedler <hi>Aqua-vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae</hi>-man, would he not take mee to be of ſmall iudgement in that Arte? And then demaunde I of him (whoſoeuer hee be) whether as meane an opinion (for his iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in very nature) may not be wel had of him, who ſeeing an heauen, which hee confeſſeth abundant in varietie of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, and they all as maruelous as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic, managed by a conſort of motions which thwart and yet diſturbe not one another: Who treading vpon an earth which yealdes breade to ſtrengthen him, wine to comfort him, golde to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich him, drugs to heale him, wonders to aſtoniſh him: who ſailing vpon a ſea, which hee knowes is water, (that is a humor naturally ſpreeding) and yet ſees it higher than the earth, that is againſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture without limit, ſolid: can yet ſurmiſe ſo hab-nab a cauſe as chance, nay anie but ſo aboue nature a cauſe as GOD could bee the compactor of this heauen the endower of this earth, the controller, of this ſea? Hee ſees huge Elements,
<pb facs="tcp:989:27"/>earth, water and aire, yet ſo ouerawde as to giue their ſubſtance, moiſture, and breath to the nouriſhing little plants and hearbes. Hee ſees fierce &amp; ſturdie beaſts, yet ſo ouerruled, as to yeelde their backs to ſeruing, their liues to feeding weake and little man: O can he doubt there is an vmpire of impeachable right, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matchable power, vnſoundable wiſdom which could, without repining, ſubiect thoſe ſo greate to theſe ſo little?</p>
            <p>Let mee beg of him (be there any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of this minde) firſt to be thinke him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe what intereſt his prince (who may commaunde his life and lande) hath in him: Then ſhould ſhee (from which wrong, thanked bee God, her highnes hath euer bene farre) hauing forced him to yeelde both into her handes, diſpoſe of the one to her Exchequer, of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to his vnderlings ſeruice, whether hee coulde brooke ſuch meaſure euen at her hande or no: whether hee would faſt to feede that vnderling of his, watch to guard him, die to ſaue him: And then ſay how deare needes muſt this title bee to all, how ſoueraine his power to all,
<pb facs="tcp:989:28"/>that at his becke, pride hath not thought much to bowe to baſenes, learning to be taught by rudeneſſe, power to be mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cled by weakeneſſe, millions to be wonne by twelue, and the earth to be caught by fiſhers. O had I now but <hi>Ananias</hi> his gift, that after the ſhining of this great light fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen &amp; earth, &amp; all vpon theſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the darkenes of this worlde, I could much them and make the ſcales fall from their eyes: how clearely ſhould they ſee, not onely that God who of nothing made them, and of moſt wretched molde bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them; but alſo that ſoule of their own, which now though their quickeſt ſence be too ſlowe to deſcrie, yet one day will their ſloweſt be quicke enough to feele. For yet, as they cannot ſee a God in his creatures, ſo neither can they a ſoule of their owne in his effects.</p>
            <p>Liue they? yet is it not by a ſoule: their temperature forſooth cannot giue them to doe ſo much: yet is this temperature of theirs of foure deads they ſay (for ſuch are the elements) and of deade added to deade can life (I am ſure) no better ariſe, than ſome what of nought multiplied by
<pb facs="tcp:989:28"/>nought: for millions of Cyphers you knowe will not raiſe ſo much as one vnit.</p>
            <p>Finde they ſomewhat in them little ſelues of capacitie enough to holde this great world &amp; it not thronged, but ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly as in a moment to preſent them with it all the heauen moouing, the ſtars ſhining, the fire mounting, the Ayre pearcing, the ſea ſwelling, the earth reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, gemmes gliſtring, varietie entertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: why euen yet is not this ſomewhat (which within ſo little as they are holdeth ſo greate as theſe are) in any caſe a ſoule; for they haue nothing in them which is not a bodie: &amp; yet euery bodie is bound, they ſay, to this lawe that it cannot holde any thing bigger than it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Feele they ſomewhat in themſelues which waxeth as the bodie waineth, and which is wiſeſt to preſcribe, when the bones &amp; ſinewes are weakeſt to execute: which enables that body now to grow moue &amp; ſpeake: which it may be ere night, hauing euery part that they ſo it now hath &amp; a greater quantity than now it hath, wil be as vnable to grow, moue or ſpeake as the dulleſt ſtone weſe: And yet ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not this
<pb facs="tcp:989:29"/>ſame what (whatſoeuer it is ſo twhart the bodie in nature, ſo ſeperat fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing it ſo perfect) obtaine of them to be other than either ſomewhat of the bodie or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the worlde. Stonie ſenceleſſe men, what can there be poſſiblie, thus to infatuate them?</p>
            <p>They could yet neuer ſee for ſooth this God, this ſoule wee ſo much talke of, <hi>Plautus</hi> (as I remember) in <hi>Aſinaria</hi> brings in an olde ſtrumpet playing vpon a worne-out cuſtomer of hers, (with whome the worlde ranne ſo lowe that he was faine to aſke daies of paiment for his pleaſure) with theſe words, <hi>Oculatae noſtra ſunt manus, credunt quod vide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t:</hi> my friend, people of our trade haue eyes in their hands, if your preſent be ſo fine they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee it, they beleeue it is ſo farre off they doe not receiue it. It is as olde as true, that like will to like: for ſee, our gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants of <hi>Diagora</hi> his religion haue kiſt their miſtriſſes ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo oft, that they are woxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen like the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, why they are come to <hi>credu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t quod vide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> too. It will not ſinke into their heads, that any this which is not ſo groſſe, it may beſeene. I maruaile whether theſe
<pb facs="tcp:989:29"/>men thinke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues breath in So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer as well as in winter: It ſhould ſeeme they doe not. For the ſharpeſt he among them ſees no breath he then ſendeth forth: But as colde growes on, and the ayre rarifies beginnes it to appeare. Fooles as they are. God and his prouidence, and their ſoules, and the like, are things of ſo ſubtil nature, that all this Sommer of their pleaſures, or harueſt of their profit, they cannot ſee them. But there is a winter of iudgement drawing on, and it ſo colde an one, that it will force a trembling of their fleſh, and gnaſhing of their teeth.</p>
            <p>Then will the ayre grow ſo ſharpe, that it will ſhewe them a God in their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, his prouidence in their damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to a (now vnbeleeued) ſoule themſelues haue, an vnſpeakable torment which in it they ſhall feele.</p>
            <p>Then ſhall they be ſo mad with paine, that they ſhall ſtare and roare, and cry <hi>O what is this I feale?</hi> It cannot be a heade, a hand, a leg, a breſt, a backe that beareth all I feele: theſe teeth haue made me rage with paine, yet was that caſe to this: this fleſh, theſe neaues, theſe ioynts, the wind
<pb facs="tcp:989:30"/>hath euen rackt, yet was it eaſe to this: It is now but a moment, yet feele I what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie can inflict vpon mee: And though I feele what it can inflict, yet will it haue ſomewhat to inflicte I neuer felt. It is that ſoule, which (then reputed fooles now founde too wife) Chriſtians taught was immortall, that taſteth all this.</p>
            <p>O that I were ſo happie as to make but one of you haue ſence of this, and that if you would bee intreated to ſpende but ſome fewe houres in marking ſome diſparing mans fit, who (though ſounde in bodie) yet in ſomewhat elſe you ſhould ſee inconceiueably panged, you could not chooſe but haue. How ioyfull ſhould I poaſt with ſuch a ſoule vnto God? with how ſweete hymnes of conſorted Angels would heauen entertaine vs? It were pride to ſay wee ſhould come to ioy but hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thicke, (that were to intimate that wee ſuppoſed one of vs were iuſt,) Noe wee ſhould both bee then ſo good (of yet ſo bad) that there ſhoulde bee for each of vs his 99. degrees of ioy a peece. But woulde there more come in &amp; our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie increaſe, O then how would that
<pb facs="tcp:989:30"/>vaulting ring? How full would each one make the number of all, and how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding all the ioy for each ones part?</p>
            <p>Now to the third, to wit the ſlight: wherein are to be denſidered two things, the pitch or hight of it, &amp; peiſe or ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of it. To botls which God himſelfe alludes <hi>Exod</hi> 19.40 where he putting his people in minde both how farre aboue the earth (as wee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erme it) of danger, and how quickly before the expectation of long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he had conducted them out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> hee tels them hee had borne them vpon Eagles winges. Of the latter ſome Grain-marians ſay, that it hath the greeke name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> becauſe it ruſhes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde with a force: And of it againe the North (that is the moſt boiſterous winde) hath the latine name of <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> becauſe it ſcoures and makes heade forward like an Eagle: And if theſe two qualities of your flight want, woe be to you, you are no Eagles.</p>
            <p>You muſt flie high: ſo did Saint <hi>Paule:</hi> his and his likes conuerſation was not lower than heauen.<note place="margin">Act. 3.20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>You muſt flie ſtrongly: ſo did <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:989:31"/>Hee had gotten to the Lord before the morning watch.<note place="margin">Pſa. 130.6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>You muſt flie high for heauen (whither you are bound) is the meaſure of hight it ſelfe;<note place="margin">Eſay. 55.9.</note> when God will ſhe we how much higher his waies are than ours, ſo much is it as are the heauens higher than the earth.</p>
            <p>You muſt flie ſtrongly: for heauen (which you would recouer) is that <hi>Iſlud quod violenti rapiant,</hi> The holde which none but ſuch as wil haue nonay, ſurprize:<note place="margin">Iud. 6.</note> the violent forſooth, (no colder) they: may take it, and they not by doring nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but by force.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe it would little boote you to heare that you muſt flie thus hie &amp; thus ſtrong, vnleſſe you withall knewe both how you might doe &amp; when you had don ſo; I will fuſt tell you the meanes to riſe, (with the note whether you be riſen) And then whence is this ſtrength, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by knowne that you haue it.</p>
            <p>The meanes firſt of riſing is to take the Apoſtles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, to ſhake off ſinne: for that which could not Iet an Angell ſtay in heauen, will not ſuffer a man to riſe from the earth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And that which ſat ſo heaue
<pb facs="tcp:989:31"/>vpon our Sauiours head, as to make him bowe his neck, ſits vpon our backes that it will not ſuffer vs to ſproede our winges: <hi>Qui peccatorum granant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſepulchris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 19.30</note> 
               <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſa obſtaculorum mole proſiltant,</hi> if wee will riſe as Chriſt did, wee muſt rowle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſtone that lies vpon vs, as hee did.</p>
            <p>The note that you are riſen, is the kinde of obiecte you haue choſen there abouts euen are you, where that is vpon which you haue ſet your delight. For from your hearts you cannot be, and where your treaſure is, there will they be. Now would you know where this obiect is? Firſt ſhew mee where your ioy is: and woulde you heare where your ioy is? tell mee where your minde is. Are you young &amp; are you wittie? whats your minde on it? Are you old &amp; are you wealthie? whats your minde on it? are you minions &amp; in fauour? whats your minde on it? Are you pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; haue your ſweet children? whats your minde on them? Then heres your ioy, for heres your minde, and Lapwing-like you crie there till you bee hoarſe, but you are but here:<note place="margin">Mat. 6.21.</note> for heres you ioy: were you once ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,
<pb facs="tcp:989:32"/>you would ſeeke the things that are aboue.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.15.</note> No farther than to the top of this ſteeple, he ſeemes (you know) ſcarce a boy in ſtature, which (when you are by him) prooues a tall man: Maruaile not though you thinke nothing in heauen worth the hauing: the reaſon is, you which grow here on earth, are ſo farre off, that all there is out of kenning.</p>
            <p>The learned in Aſtronomie, haue by demonſtration founde that the Moone (which the ignorant thinke the biggeſt ſtarre but the Sun) is indeede the leaſt Plannet. But <hi>Mercurie</hi> (which is your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening ſtarre) though it ſeeme the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt (but theſe two) is in truthbut the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt of all the reſt. But aſke you of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> why they ſeeme ſo big, they will returne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are low. Things of this world, as for their ſhort laſting &amp; often changing they haue bin likned to the Moone, whoſe motion is moſt ſwift &amp; face moſt diuerſe: So alſo for their pliableneſſe to any vſe: wherinlike their maſter man, <hi>Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iuſto ſunt iuſti, cum peruerſo peruertuntur,</hi> Such are they as hee imployes them: like vnto <hi>Mercurie,</hi> who hath this propertie that
<pb facs="tcp:989:32"/>hee is good or bad as the ſtarre is with whome hee is ioyned. But ſee, they agree with theſe two in more than ſo; they borrowe alſo their faire ſhew they make vs of their neereneſſe to vs, and therefore ſeeme they bigger becauſe they are lower than better thinges. Had wee taken the two winges of the morning (prayer and meditation) for his, as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>apprebenditur ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitas ſcalae,</hi> by theſe we may ſoare to the top of <hi>Iacobs</hi> ladder: Quickly ſhould we haue deſcryed both this ſo ſophiſtica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted greatneſſe of thinges tranſitorie, and ſo conueied infinitneſſe of eternall glorie.</p>
            <p>Now concerning the ſtrength of your flight, and both the meanes for it, and the triall of it, <hi>Paule</hi> hath together de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered them in the 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4.</p>
            <p>The meanes, if you bee mighty through GOD: the triall, if your proceedings bee ſterne, that noe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment can withholde you from him. For if you bee once thus win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, downe muſt euen <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable houldes before you. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:989:33"/>fore will I ſaie the leſſe of both. For as for thes meanes, I am perſwaded, there is none preſent ſo ſelfe conceipted, as (in colde bloode) to impute it to anie other, but him, who put thoſe ſinewes into <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> armes as coulde breake a bowe of braſſe.<note place="margin">Pſa. 18.34</note> Onelie to aduertiſe fleh and bloode to ſtand euer on his guard (that ſo preſumptuous a thought neuer ſteale vpon it by conſequent, as to clame the leaſt part in this honour) I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale what olde <hi>Lactan.</hi> hath to this point excellently noted,<note place="margin">Tull. de Natur. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> who by the very <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of Iupiters name, which came as the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then ſaide, <hi>a iuuando</hi> of helping, conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to them hee could be no God: <hi>Iuua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, opus aliquid confere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis,</hi> he onely is ſaide to helpe which doth leſſe than all that is doone.</p>
            <p>Of the tokens of this ſtrength, (to witte the ouerbearing hinderances that oppoſe themſelues, which will appeare by our ſpeedie recouerie of the place, towardes which wee make, I will ſay as little. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let reſolution learne, this of mee: it is not yet reſolute enough, if this world haue ought at which thou rubbe: If a kingdom
<pb facs="tcp:989:33"/>caſt in your way, marke your ſtart, you haue ſicke fethers in your wing, and for your ſpeede, builde not vpon <hi>Mercedem adepti vnd-cimae horae operarij,</hi> they had their pence which came in the laſt houre: But remember it was not <hi>operis</hi> (as <hi>Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary</hi> ſaith) <hi>ſed miſcricordiae,</hi> his mercie that gaue them, not their worke that ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them. And then thinke wee may well miſſe of this mercie, which we know hath beene ſo ſtrange, as to giue no eare to ſo great Suite as knocking, and of ſo yong and innocent as Virgins.</p>
            <p>And this of the third Note of an Eagle, (her flight high and ſtrong:) now of the Foe, which is the Dragon: for ſo writes the Poet.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nunc in reluctantes Dracones,</l>
               <l>Egit amor dapis,<note place="margin">Horat. car. lib. 4. ode. 4.</note> at que pugnae.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The Eagle is no ſooner ſligded, but ſtraight ſhe is grapling with the Dragon. And heeres a right note of an Eagle indeede to ſingle ſuch an enemie, who hath bene thouſandes of yeares in armes againſt his God. <hi>Ierones</hi> his head would
<pb facs="tcp:989:34"/>now giue proofe of a good ſubiect to his prince; but this Dragons head of a better to his God. Should we turne taile to this foe, wee ſhoulde doe what in vs lies to make both God a lier, &amp; our ſelues per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iured, He hath promiſed to put an edge in<note place="margin">Gen. 3.15</note> vs againſt him, (I will put enmity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene this feede and her head) And that this enemy ſhould grow to encou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter him, &amp; wound him in the verie head, Hee ſhall bruiſe thy very head: And wee our ſelues haue vndertaken in our baptiſme, to do as much.</p>
            <p>You haue often herad how careful <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiball</hi> was of maintaining the quarrell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Romaines,</hi> which his father <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malcar</hi> had ſworne him to. And you haue often heard, how harde God preſſed the diſobedient <hi>Iewes</hi> with the <hi>Rhecabits</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruance of their fathers charge. Put theſe together: Shall not heathen <hi>Hanniball</hi> riſe in iudgement againſt vs, if we riſe not in courage againſt this Dragon, againſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue paſſed an oath ſtill to be in armes? Were the loſſe ſmall by his friendſhip, it were another matter. But it coſt vs (if wee remember) Paradiſe. Or were the gaine
<pb facs="tcp:989:34"/>but ſmall by this conqueſt, it were ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matter: But it is euen that or greater, for which once we ventured.</p>
            <p>All we ſhall be like (not <hi>Dij,</hi> Gods that are ſo baſe to haue fellowes, but) <hi>Deus</hi> that one God that is aboue al &amp; in all. And how ſo? He made all good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo (ſaith <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigen</hi>) in a ſort ſhall we doe, <hi>Nobis ſaltem, qui malis aduer ſamur,</hi> wee ſhall make the Diuell him ſelfe good vnto vs, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of whom ſhall be the matter of our glorie.</p>
            <p>Nowlong you to be bickering with him, and woulde any of you know where to finde him? Aſke <hi>Macarius,</hi> he wil tell you: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> heere man here is his forme: when God bids you be angrie with the Dragon, he bids you be angrie with your ſelues; and when hee wils you to fight againſt him, he wils you to fight againſt your owne luſt; for they (as the Apoſtle hath giuen you intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence) fight againſt you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leo</hi> in his ſermon of the 7. of <hi>Macab.</hi> hath deſcried within you, a whole <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſcado</hi> of his: couetouſnes, which tell mee citizens if you neuer founde there:
<pb facs="tcp:989:35"/>pride, which tell me Ladies if you neuer found there: Anger, which tell me Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines if you neuer founde there: Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, which tell mee Courtiers if you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer founde there: Lies, which tell mee Lawyers if you neuer found there. And if you euer did, doe (as there bee wiſhes you) <hi>Cum viderit is multiplicem pugnam, numer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſam quaerite victoriam,</hi> Set vpon all there, and get many crownes for many conqueſts.</p>
            <p>One ſaith, a Captaine and his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie is like a birde, whereof the Captaine is the bodie which mooueth the winge, and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie the winges which beare vp the bodie. As therefore if you can breake the winges you may eaſilie ſeize vpon the birde; So if you can cut off theſe forces of the Dragon (which are his wings) you ſhall! at pleaſure catch him which is the bodie. And thus briefly of the Foe, the fourth note of an Eagle.</p>
            <p>The fiſt (if you remember) was the Age, and that of the nature that it might be renewed. And this is that peculiar of the Soints,<note place="margin">Iob. 11.17</note> which was <hi>Zephers</hi> warrant to promiſe iuſt <hi>Iobe</hi> that his age ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:989:35"/>ſhine and appeare more cleare than the moone day:<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.23.</note> And <hi>Paules</hi> commiſſion to enioyne the conuerted <hi>Epheſians</hi> to ſo greate a taſke as to bee renewed in the ſpirit of their minde: And <hi>Auguſtines</hi> grounde, for that note of his vpon <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> ſacrifice in the 15. of <hi>Gen.</hi> where, though the age of euerie beaſt hee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered bee ſet downe, (his Ramme, his Goate, each three yeare olde) yet of his birdes (by which, Spiritual men are ment) he are wee no ſuch thing: <hi>De auium ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taete tacetur,</hi> they haue ſpecified no ſtint of yeares,<note place="margin">Eſay. 40.31.</note> becauſe they haue indee de no ende of yeares. Now this reparing of the Eagle is in two points, The melting her ſoarefethers, &amp; the caſting her ouergrown bill, <hi>Plin. lib.</hi> 10. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. (For the former of which her meanes is, as ſome <hi>Hebrewes.</hi> write, to bath in a ſpring: for the latter with <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> the ſtreame of waters accord, to beate it againſt a rocke:) E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo haue the choſen ones of God, both two meanes, and two degrees of their reuocation.</p>
            <p>The firſt of their meanes, baptiſme; anſwerable to her bathing.<note place="margin">Gal. 3.27.</note> For as many
<pb facs="tcp:989:36"/>of vs as are baptized haue put on Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The ſecond,<note place="margin">2. Co. 1.10.</note> Repentance, like her bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt the Rock: for both as paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is it, hauing ſorrow for his mother, of whom it is bred;<note place="margin">Act. 11.18</note> and it is fruitfull ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing life for his daughter which it brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth forth.</p>
            <p>The firſt of their degres, <hi>Viuification,</hi> or a ſpiritual ioy, vpon a feeling they haue of pardon for hauing done amiſſe, and ſtrength hereafter to doe better.</p>
            <p>The other their <hi>Glorification</hi> (or the change of their corruption into the ſtate of Angels by their reſurrection.)</p>
            <p>Of the former, wee haue one example in <hi>Paule,</hi> now ſo woe begone, as to break out into <hi>Owretched man that I am, who ſhal deliuer me from this bodie of death?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.25.</note> 
               <hi>I thanke God through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> neuer more deſperate diſeaſe, neuer more quicke cure.</p>
            <p>For the latter, they haue his worde, whoſe credit is ſo good that hee needes not the teſtimonie of men. In the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection they ſhall bee like the Angels of God in heauen:<note place="margin">Ma. 22.30</note> though not with out bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies as they, yet as free from corruption
<pb facs="tcp:989:36"/>as they. But of this I haue elſewhere ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at large.</p>
            <p>Here my note is, that euery one who will goe for an Eagle, muſt both molt and replume. Shall I ſpeake plaine?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide pro. cap.</hi> 24. v. 16.</note> muſt ſo ſearch euerie corner in his heart for ſinne, till hee finde himſelfe almoſt as farre gone as euen now you heard <hi>Paule</hi> was. They bee the broken hearts Chriſt came to heale. The whole in opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (for in truthe there are none) they either haue noe neede, or ſhall haue noe vſe of his phiſicke. But you muſt not ſtay here. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, God hath two knees, a left one of iudgement, and a right one of mercie. If thou be a ſinner (and therefore on his left hand) thou muſt indeede take his left knee in thy way till thou tremble for feare: But the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by it creep to the right, which wil make the ſpring for ioy.</p>
            <p>Heare ſecure wantons, from whome ſin yet neuer wrong teare, whom the <hi>Viol de la Iambo,</hi> hath a charge to keepe from melancholie, looke vp &amp; ſee another Viol that wil one day as much noble all your ſences, as that delighteth one: It is a Violl
<pb facs="tcp:989:37"/>of wrath which ſhall bee powred vpon you.<note place="margin">Reuel. 16.1.</note> Weepe a while to ſaue a howling for euer: Come molt, you are yet no Eagles.</p>
            <p>And heere drooping ſpirits (bee there any preſent) who languiſh in deſpaire, if this earth haue Eagles, you (of all men) ſure are they, you haue molted, you haue knockt your bils againſt the Rocke: let it ſuffice. O cheere at laſt and pray for vs who neuer had the grace to doe ſo much: if euer any came to ſuffer with Chriſt, it cannot bee but you are they from whom torment hath wrong, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken mee.</hi> And then bid that diſputer ſay, how you can miſſe of raigning with him, who when hee had promiſed you ſhould doe ſo, (to exclude pretence of doubt) ſent that his promiſe with a letter (as it were of commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) to you, that if hee were true, who neuer can bee falſe in that hee was trueth it ſelfe, It is a faithfull ſaying, <hi>Eſt &amp; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> hath proteſted it, you which haue ſuffered with him ſhall raigne with him, <hi>Eſt &amp; Amen</hi> hath promiſed it.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.</note> And this briefly of the Age, the fiſt of my notes of an Eagle.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:989:37"/>The ſixt was her wit, (ſeene in her cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to peife or weigh her prey, before ſhee attempt to flie with it.) <hi>Rapta non protiaus ferans, ſed primè deponuns,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Plin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>) expertaque pondus tum demùm ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eunt:</hi> the manner of theſe birds is not to ſnach and away, but firſt to trie how hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie that is they ſeaze on, and if they finde it portable, then to bee gone with it.</p>
            <p>Man indeede is the Lord of al creatures, yet oft fareth it with him, as once it did with Lord <hi>Naaman,</hi> vouchſafing not to bee aduiſed by ſome ſeruants of his, It is a venture but hee wil Hooſe ſo greate a bleſſing, as a cleanſing from his leproſie, for ſo ſmall paines as a waſhing in <hi>Iordan,</hi> Piſmires, they muſt teach him diligence in making his prouiſion, or hee will bee to ſeeke of neceſſaries, Lillyes they muſt learne him confidence, to builde vpon Gods care of him, or hee will haue loſt the memorie of his prouidence. And Eagles th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y muſt teach him diſcretion, to conſider what hee gaines, or hee will be ſo headie, to ingage himſelfe for that, the gaine of which will venter him his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:989:38"/>ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ananias</hi> found it to be true,<note place="margin">Act. 5. ſer. 59.</note> 
               <hi>dum prety quarit compendium, anunaefecit detrimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ambroſe:</hi> while hee was ſo ſlie as to ſaue his money, he prooued ſo raſh as to looſe his ſoule. And ſo did <hi>Gehezy,</hi> while hee weighed not the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and raiment, would ouer-loade his owne ſoule with that which loaded two Syrians backes: hee caſt himſelfe into ſuch a heate of ſinne, that it broake out v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him into an hereditarie leproſie.</p>
            <p>Heere bee greate preyes to be found by trading in this Citie, but they haue oft an oath, or lie hanging at them: theſe will bee ſo heauie on your ſoules they wil preſſe you downe to hell: theſe woulde bee left alone.</p>
            <p>There be great preyes to be founde by preſentments in the Church, but they haue oft a waightie leaſe or ſomewhat els hanging at them: weigh theſe leafes (both demiſors and receiuers) you ſhall finde that they will coſt you the Fee ſimple of a better thing: Theſe would bee left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</p>
            <p>There bee alſo perhaps great preyes
<pb facs="tcp:989:38"/>to bee founde in ſome Courts, by abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poore Vniuerſities ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t priuiledges: but weigh the priuiledges I beſeech you, leaſt they prooue (more than by their name they ſeeme) not <hi>Legis,</hi> but <hi>Euangelij priuationes,</hi> &amp; bereaue you of the comfore of the very Goſpell. I cannot doubt either of the wiſdom or the conſcience, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hearing of this matter is referred: but yet giue mee leaue (out of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance) of my duetie too, and my feare for my mother) in the name of learning and vertue to intreate you, that as you will not haue your memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſtincke in the noſes of all learned po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie, as you will not vnawares take from that pretogatiue to which you woulde ſeeme to adde, by diſabling it to giue that, which you ſay it muſt needs recall: As you will not bee able for that ſlaunder to the preaching of the goſpell; that it hath taught, to take from learning that which ignorance perſwaded to giue it, you would in your determination herof vſe both your wiſdom &amp; your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience.</p>
            <p>There bee greate preyer to be found by counterfaite repriſall at Sea, but
<pb facs="tcp:989:39"/>they haue oft a conſcience of piracy hanging at them. Theſe are ſo heauie they will ſinke you in a burning lake: Theſe woulde be left alone,</p>
            <p>There is indede a kinde of baſtard Eagle, termed <hi>Halietus,</hi> (as who would ſay the Sea Eagle:) See wanteth this forecaſt I talke of; She will ſowſe at any fiſh ſhe ſees, but ſhe paies for this her hearts, (that oft befals her, as the writers of the naturall hiſtorie recorde) <hi>Vt cum ferre quod caperet ne que at; in gurgitem demer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatur:</hi> That being not able to lift vp that ſhee faſtened on, ſhee is drawne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der water and drowned. But theſe (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member) are not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> right bredde, and likelie to bee drenched before they bee gathered hither.</p>
            <p>Phiſitions for the bodie, deuide their whole practiſe into two generall partes: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (or preuenting phiſicke,) and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (or recouering phiſicke.) The former not ſo troubleſome, but conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moſt in keeping of a wholſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et: The latter very painefull, as in taking of it there muſt bee purgings, ſweat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, lancings, and the like.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:989:39"/>Wee for the ſoule haue two parts of our practiſe too: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant that it will neuer trouble you, and that is this weighing diſcretion in the gettings (to which now I woulde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade,) And <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (another bitter one) of hauing eaſe by lancing your own hearts, and by confeſſing that which you would now thinke a death the worlde ſhoulde knowe, which you ſhall bee forced to vſe, accept you not of this.</p>
            <p>If you make this rule vnto your ſelues, to gaine nothing but with a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, all the comfort you ſhall haue of it my heart is not able to conceiue. But this I know you ſhall finde, to liue in credit with men, to die at peace with God, and to ſcape thoſe pangs, which when you feele them, you would bee wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to buy out with the loſſe of all you haue.</p>
            <p>But if all bee fiſh with you that comes to net, and any thing to be done wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſomething may bee gotten, then ſay vpon your death-beds that I lie, if there either you bee not giuen ouer to haue no remorſe at all, and ſo to goe to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb facs="tcp:989:40"/>like fooles to the ſtockes:) or, if you finde the mercie to haue remorſe, betweene a ſetled reſolution, you ſhall heare that there is no ſaluation without reſtitution, &amp; impoſſible you ſhould ſeeke to make this reſtitution, when you finde not ſcarce any other meanes than to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire and die.</p>
            <p>And this I thought good to obſerue by occaſion of theſe ſixe notes of an Eagle, the kinde of birde by which our Sauiour choſe to ſhadowe them who ſhall bee gathered hither. Now it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth that from this choice of the Fliers, I proceede to thoſe neare cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances in the flight it ſelfe, contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in theſe wordes, <hi>ſhall bee gathered together:</hi> which as I conceiue them are three.</p>
            <p>The firſt, the efficient cauſe of it, or hee in whoſe ſtrength it is made.</p>
            <p>The ſeconde, the manner or after what ſort it ſhall bee made.</p>
            <p>The thirde, the certaintie or the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance wee haue that it muſt bee made. All three diſtinctly deliuered vs in that one Originall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which wee in
<pb facs="tcp:989:40"/>engliſh expreſſe by theſe many words <hi>ſhall bee gathered together.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt of which notes (or the efficient cauſe) I gather by <hi>Abnega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> out of the voice of this Verbe, which beeing Paſſiue, giueth to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande that they who ſhall be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red are no Actors in their owne gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</p>
            <p>The ſeconde (or the manner of this Flight) I finde in the Praepoſition <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which impoſing vpon the Verbe, (that is compounded with it) a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitie, as the Grammarians ſpeake (indeede ſtretching the action or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it to manie) argueth in this ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering a ſhoaling or an aſſembling of ſome companie.</p>
            <p>The thirde (or the certainetie of this flight) I deduce out of the nature of this Verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> it ſelfe, which at leaſt importeth a preheminence, and not ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome an vnreſiſtable violence in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducting, or as one woulde ſay a ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigntie in drawing, whither it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynes a neceſſitie of following. For ſo vſeth <hi>Aeſebines</hi> it, with whome <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:989:41"/>ſoundes as much as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to drag or haile one to the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>, no leſſe than to leaue him no ſhift whereby to eſcape making his anſwere: or, to ſpeake more to the capacitie of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; firſt in that it is ſaide, theſe Eagles ſhall bee gathered, I conclude that it is not they that ſhall gather themſelues: Then in that it is added, in that they ſhall bee gathered together, I collecte there muſt bee ſome number of them who ſhall be gathered: Laſt in that it is tolde vs that they ſhall bee gathered or inforced to make this appearance, I reſolue they ſhall not haue power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie it, out come they muſt.</p>
            <p>By the gathering I tolde you in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning was the reſurrection meant, and therefore cannot now doubt but you conceiue that by the cauſe in this gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is the Author of our reſurrection, By the certainetie of this gathering is the aſſurance of our reſurrection vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode.</p>
            <p>Now concerning that which I had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in each of theſe three, I haue place onely for our Sauiours complainte,
<pb facs="tcp:989:41"/>
               <hi>Iohn.</hi> 16.12. I haue many things to ſay, but you cannot beare them away; not that your capacities would not ſerue to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them for their greatnes, but that my ſtrength cannot laſt to deliuer them, for their number. For beſides what I had intended of the two firſt points (the cauſe, &amp; the manner) with the ſumme of which,<note place="margin">Mor. 24.</note> I ſhould haue bene better able in fewe wordes to acquaint you, my eſpeciall purpoſe was (in the thirde) to haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted the making good vnto the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts</hi> of our time that, which long time <hi>Gregory</hi> vndertooke to their fathers in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie, that <hi>Reſurrections fidem qui in obedientia non tenent, eaudem in ratione de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buerant teners:</hi> They whoſe faith was ſo weake, that they could not therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue a Reſurrection, becauſe God had promiſed it; ſhould yet in reaſon haue made no doubt of it, becauſe very reaſon in a ſort perſwaded it.</p>
            <p>But heere as the ſtraitnes of time hath preuented me (for vttering that which it may be might haue done ſome good) ſo hath it made me amendes with bidding me to the keeping of that beſt
<pb facs="tcp:989:42"/>rule, giuen but in one, (but true in euery ſuch miſterie of religion) which otherwiſe I ſhould haue ventured to haue broken, <hi>Fides credat, intelligentia non requirat,</hi> Let faith beleeue it, let wit ſeeke no reaſon of it: <hi>Ne aut non inuentum putet incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile, aut reperium non credat ſingulare,</hi> leaſt curioſitie for his paines gaine one of theſe two thinges, either (if it bee in iudgement dazeled and cannot finde it) like an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtata to thinke it incredible: or, (if it bee in mercie illightned and able to reach it) then (like almoſt as ill) to eſteeme it no more than ordinarie.</p>
            <p>Howſoeuer therefore, either in an other place or at another time in this argument I may venture to doe as ſwimmers vſe, &amp; put my ſelfe to diuing to ſaue others from drowning (for ſo much danger is there in ſeeking to eſtabliſh that by reaſon which is aboue reaſon:) here &amp; now, that one promiſe of him (who is the trueth it ſelfe, that all that are in their graue, ſhall heare the voice of the ſonne of God) ſhal ſuffice mee both for direction to the Author &amp; intelligence of the companie,<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.28.</note> and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Apparance vpon this Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:989:42"/>The Sonne of God (whoſe voice ſhall bee heard) hee ſaith, my ſoule ſhall bee the Author, that All which ſhall heare it, they ſhall be the companie, and that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which ſhall be reſtored vnto them, ſhall bee the warrant they ſhall riſe.</p>
            <p>Now the God of wiſdome and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation giue vs both (in our ſearching) mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie, and (in our ſuffering) faith, that to vs may the comfort redound, and the checke not ſtretch of our Sauiours <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The body which was ſlaine for vs, quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vs: which is vnited to vs, ſanctifie vs: which feeds vs, ſtrengthen vs: which ſhall iudge vs, acquite vs.</p>
            <p>The maieſtie (at whoſe commandement the Eagle mounteth) aſlure vs of our kinde, by our neſt ſo ſure as on the rock, our eye ſo ſtrong as vnd aſeled by the Sun, our flight ſo true, as high and ſwift, our Foe ſo choyce as the Dragon; our age ſo freſh as renewed: our wit ſo diſcreere as peizing before bearing away: And laſt the Sonne, who wee know ſhal at laſt raiſe vs all out of the ſleepe of death, in
<pb facs="tcp:989:43"/>the meane time raiſe vs his people out of our ſlumber in ſinne, that our firſt life may ſecure vs from the ſeconde death. To this Son, with the Father, and the holy Ghoſt (three perſons but one God, power, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and loue it ſelfe) be aſcribed al praiſe dominion &amp; glorie, now and for euermore</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:989:43"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
